As someone who has spent his entire career trying to be invisible
كشخص قضى طوال أوقات مهنته يحاول أن يكون متخفياً،
standing in front of an audience is a cross between
فالوقوف أمام جمهور هو خليط بين
an out-of-body experience and a deer caught in the headlights,
تجربة الخروج من الجسد ورؤية غزال على مصابيح السيارة الأمامية ،
so please forgive me for violating one of the TED commandments
لذا أعذروني على إنتهاك أحدى وصايا تيد
by relying on words on paper,
بالإعتماد على الكلمات من الورق،
and I only hope I'm not struck by lightning bolts before I'm done.
وأرجو فقط أن لا اصاب برهبة " الاضواء المسلطة علي " لحين انتهائي
I'd like to begin by talking about some of the ideas that motivated me
أود أن أبدأ بالحديث عن بعض الأفكار التي دفعتني
to become a documentary photographer.
لأصبح مصوّراً وثائقياً.
I was a student in the '60s, a time of social upheaval and questioning,
لقد كنت طالباً في الستينات، وقت الإضطرابات الإجتماعية والإستجوابات،
and on a personal level, an awakening sense of idealism.
وعلى المستوى الشخصي، حس مثالي بالصحوة.
The war in Vietnam was raging;
كانت الحرب في فيتنام مندلعة،
the Civil Rights Movement was under way;
وحركة الحقوق المدنية متأججة،
and pictures had a powerful influence on me.
وكان للصور تأثير جبّار عليّ.
Our political and military leaders were telling us one thing,
كان قادتنا السياسيين والعسكريين يخبرونا بشئ،
and photographers were telling us another.
وتخبرنا الصور بشئ آخر.
I believed the photographers, and so did millions of other Americans.
لقد آمنت بالتصوير، وكذلك ملايين من الأمريكيين الآخرين.
Their images fueled resistance to the war and to racism.
لقد غذت صورهم معارضة الحرب والعنصرية.
They not only recorded history; they helped change the course of history.
لم يقوموا فقط بتسجيل التاريخ، لقد ساعدوا في تغيير دورة التاريخ.
Their pictures became part of our collective consciousness
أصبحت صورهم جزءا من وعينا الاجتماعي
and, as consciousness evolved into a shared sense of conscience,
وكما يتطور الوعي إلى شعور مشترك بالضمير.،
change became not only possible, but inevitable.
لم يصبح التغيير ممكناً فقط، بل لا مفر منه.
I saw that the free flow of information represented by journalism,
لقد رأيت أن التدفق الحُر للمعلومات تمثلها الصحافة،
specifically visual journalism, can bring into focus
خصوصاً الصحافة المرئية على وجه التحديد، يمكن أن تجذب الإنتباه
both the benefits and the cost of political policies.
لكلا الفوائد وتكاليف السياسات.
It can give credit to sound decision-making, adding momentum to success.
يمكنها أن تعطي مصداقية لإتخاذ القرار، معطيةً زخماً للنجاح.
In the face of poor political judgment or political inaction,
في مواجهة الحكم السياسي الضعيف أو التراخي السياسي،
it becomes a kind of intervention, assessing the damage
تصبح نوعاً من التدخل، تقييم الأضرار
and asking us to reassess our behavior.
وتطالبنا بإعادة تقييم تصرفاتنا.
It puts a human face on issues
إنها تضع البشر في مواجهة القضايا
which from afar can appear abstract
التي تبدو من على البعد تجريدية
or ideological or monumental in their global impact.
أو إيديلوجية أو أثرية في تأثيرها العالمي.
What happens at ground level, far from the halls of power,
ما يحدث على مستوى الأرض، بعيداً عن قاعات السلطة،
happens to ordinary citizens one by one.
يحدث لمواطنين عاديين واحد تلو الآخر.
And I understood that documentary photography
وأنا أفهم أن التصوير الوثائقي
has the ability to interpret events from their point of view.
لديه القدرة على ترجمة الأحداث من وجهات نظرها.
It gives a voice to those who otherwise would not have a voice.
إنه يعطي الصوت لأؤلئك الذين لا صوت لهم بدونها.
And as a reaction, it stimulates public opinion
وكرد فعل، فانها تحفّز الرأي العام
and gives impetus to public debate,
وتعطي زخماً للنقاش العام،
thereby preventing the interested parties
وبالتالي منع الأطراف المعنية
from totally controlling the agenda, much as they would like to.
من التحكم المطلق بالأجندة، كثيراً كما يرغبون بذلك.
Coming of age in those days made real
بلوغ الرشد في تلك الأيام أثبت حقيقة
the concept that the free flow of information is absolutely vital
مفهوم أن التدفق الحر للمعلومات أمر حيوي للغاية
for a free and dynamic society to function properly.
لمجتمع حُرّ وديناميكي ليعمل بصورة صحيحة.
The press is certainly a business, and in order to survive
الصحافة بالتأكيد هي عمل تجاري، و من أجل البقاء
it must be a successful business,
ينبغي أن تكون عملاً ناجحاً،
but the right balance must be found
لكن لابد من إيجاد التوازن الصحيح
between marketing considerations and journalistic responsibility.
بين إعتبارات التسويق والمسؤولية الصحفية.
Society's problems can't be solved until they're identified.
مشاكل المجتمع لا يمكن حلها إلا إذا تم تحديدها.
On a higher plane, the press is a service industry,
وعلى مستوى أعلى، فان الصحافة هي قطاع خدمي،
and the service it provides is awareness.
والخدمة التي تقدمها هي الوعي.
Every story does not have to sell something.
لا ينبغي لكل قصة أن تبيع شيئاً ما.
There's also a time to give.
هناك أيضاً وقت للعطاء.
That was a tradition I wanted to follow.
كانت تلك تقاليد رغبت في إتباعها.
Seeing the war created such incredibly high stakes for everyone involved
برؤية أن الحرب أحدثت مثل هذه المخاطر الكبيرة لجميع المشاركين
and that visual journalism could actually become a factor in conflict resolution --
وأن بمستطاع الصحافة المرئية أن تصبح عاملاً في حلّ الصراعات،
I wanted to be a photographer in order to be a war photographer.
أردت أن أصبح مصوراً من أجل أن أصبح مصوّراً للحرب.
But I was driven by an inherent sense
لكني كنت مدفوعاً بإحساس متوارث
that a picture that revealed the true face of war
بأن الصورة التي كشفت الوجه الحقيقي للحرب
would almost by definition be an anti-war photograph.
ستكون بحسب التعريف صورة مناهضة للحرب.
I'd like to take you on a visual journey through some of the events
أرغب في أخذكم إلى رحلة مرئية عبر بعض الأحداث
and issues I've been involved in over the past 25 years.
والقضايا التي شاركت فيها خلال ال 25 سنة الماضية.
In 1981, I went to Northern Ireland.
عام 1981، ذهبت إلى شمال إيرلندا.
10 IRA prisoners were in the process of starving themselves to death
كان 10 سجناء للجيش الإيرلندي في مرحلة تجويع أنفسهم حتى الموت
in protest against conditions in jail.
في إحتجاج على الأوضاع داخل السجن.
The reaction on the streets was violent confrontation.
كان رد الفعل في الشوارع هو مواجهات عنيفة.
I saw that the front lines of contemporary wars
لقد رأيت أن الخطوط الأمامية للحروب المعاصرة
are not on isolated battlefields, but right where people live.
ليست في ميادين القتال المعزولة، لكن بالقرب من حيث يعيش الناس.
During the early '80s, I spent a lot of time in Central America,
خلال بداية الثمانينات، قضيت الكثير من الوقت في أمريكا الوسطى،
which was engulfed by civil wars
التي حاقت بها الحروب الأهلية
that straddled the ideological divide of the Cold War.
التي قللت الفجوة الإيديلوجية للحرب الباردة.
In Guatemala, the central government --
في غواتيمالا، الحكومة المركزية --
controlled by a oligarchy of European decent --
المسيطر عليها من قلة من الأوروبيين البيض--
was waging a scorched Earth campaign against an indigenous rebellion,
والذين يشنون حملات الأرض المحروقة ضد تمرد السكان الأصليين،
and I saw an image that reflected the history of Latin America:
لقد رأيت الصورة التي تعبّر عن تاريخ أمريكا اللاتينية:
conquest through a combination of the Bible and the sword.
الفتح من خلال جمع ما بين الإنجيل والسيف.
An anti-Sandinista guerrilla was mortally wounded
عصابات معادية للالساندينية أصيبت بجروح بالغة
as Commander Zero attacked a town in Southern Nicaragua.
حيث هجم "القائد صفر" على قرية في جنوب نيكراغوا.
A destroyed tank belonging to Somoza's national guard
دبابة مدمرة تتبع لحرس سوموزا الوطني
was left as a monument in a park in Managua,
تُركت كنصب تذكاري في حديقة في ماناغوا،
and was transformed by the energy and spirit of a child.
وقد تغيرت بروح وطاقة الطفل.
At the same time, a civil war was taking place in El Salvador,
في نفس الوقت، كانت الحرب الأهلية تبدأ في السلفادور،
and again, the civilian population was caught up in the conflict.
ومجدداً، حُوصر المدنيين في الصراع.
I've been covering the Palestinian-Israeli conflict since 1981.
لقد كنت أقوم بتغطية الصراع الفلسطيني الإسرائيلي منذ عام 1981.
This is a moment from the beginning of the second intifada, in 2000,
هذه اللحظة من بداية الإنتفاضة الثانية ، عام 2000،
when it was still stones and Molotovs against an army.
عندما كانت ما تزال قذائف المولوتوف ضد الجيش.
In 2001, the uprising escalated into an armed conflict,
وفي عام 2001، تصاعدت الإنتفاضة إلى عمل مسلح،
and one of the major incidents was
وكانت أحدى الحوادث الرئيسية هي
the destruction of the Palestinian refugee camp
تدمير مخيم اللاجئين الفلسطيني
in the West Bank town of Jenin.
في مدينة جنين على الضفة الغربية.
Without the political will to find common ground,
وبدون أن يجد عالم السياسيين الأرضية المشتركة،
the continual friction of tactic and counter-tactic
فان الإحتكاك المستمر للتكتيك والتكتيك المضاد
only creates suspicion and hatred and vengeance,
يخلق الشك والكراهية والانتقام ،
and perpetuates the cycle of violence.
ويديم دوامة العنف.
In the '90s, after the breakup of the Soviet Union,
في أعوام التسعينات، بعد تفكك الإتحاد السوفيتي،
Yugoslavia fractured along ethnic fault lines, and civil war broke out
بدأت يوغوسلافيا في التصدع على الجانب العرقي، وبدأت الحرب الأهلية
between Bosnia, Croatia and Serbia.
بين البوسنة، كرواتيا وصربيا.
This is a scene of house-to-house fighting in Mostar,
هذا هو مشهد قتال بين منزل ومنزل في موسطار،
neighbor against neighbor.
جار يقاتل جاره.
A bedroom, the place where people share intimacy,
غرفة نوم، المكان الذي يتشارك فيه الناس الإلفة،
where life itself is conceived, became a battlefield.
حيث تتكون الحياة نفسها، يصبح ساحة معركة.
and was used as a makeshift morgue.
وكان يُستخدم كمشرحة مؤقتة.
Dead Serbian soldiers were collected after a battle
قتلى الجنود الصرب تم جمعهم بعد المعركة
and used as barter for the return of prisoners
وأُستخدموا للمقايضة بالسجناء
or Bosnian soldiers killed in action.
أو الجنود البوسنيين الذين قتلوا في الأحداث.
This was once a park.
كانت هذه حديقة سابقاً.
The Bosnian soldier who guided me
الجندي البوسني الذي أرشدني
told me that all of his friends were there now.
أخبرني بأن كل أصدقائه كانوا هناك الآن.
At the same time in South Africa,
في نفس الوقت في جنوب أفريقيا،
after Nelson Mandela had been released from prison,
بعد أن تم إطلاق سراح نيلسون مانديلا من السجن،
the black population commenced the final phase
بدأ السكان السود في المرحلة النهائية
of liberation from apartheid.
للتحرر من نظام الفصل العنصري.
One of the things I had to learn as a journalist
أحد الأشياء التي توجب عليّ تعلمها كصحفي
was what to do with my anger.
كان هو التحكم في غضبي.
I had to use it, channel its energy, turn it into something
كان يتوجب علي القيام به، تمرير غضبي، وتحويله إلى شئ
that would clarify my vision, instead of clouding it.
يقوم بتوضيح رؤيتي، بدلاً عن تهميشه.
In Transkei, I witnessed a rite of passage into manhood, of the Xhosa tribe.
في ترانسكي، شهدت طقوس العبور إلى مرحلة الرجولة، لقبيلة الكسوزا.
Teenage boys lived in isolation, their bodies covered with white clay.
عاش المراهقون في عُزلة، تم تغطية أجسادهم بالطين الأبيض.
After several weeks, they washed off the white
وبعد عدة أسابيع، تم غسلهم من الطين الأبيض
and took on the full responsibilities of men.
وأستلموا كامل مسؤولية الرجال.
It was a very old ritual that seemed symbolic
وكانت طقوس قديمة جدا على ما يبدو رمزا
Children in Soweto playing on a trampoline.
أطفال يلعبون في سويتو على الترامبولين.
Elsewhere in Africa there was famine.
في أماكن أخرى في أفريقيا كانت هناك مجاعة.
In Somalia, the central government collapsed and clan warfare broke out.
في الصومال، أنهارت الحكومة المركزية وأندلعت الحرب العشائرية.
Farmers were driven off their land,
غادر المزارعون أراضيهم،
and crops and livestock were destroyed or stolen.
ودُمرت المحاصيل والماشية أو سُرقت.
Starvation was being used as a weapon of mass destruction --
كان التجويع يُستخدم كسلاح للدمار الشامل--
primitive but extremely effective.
بدائي لكنه فعّال بشدة.
Hundreds of thousands of people were exterminated,
مئات الآلاف من الناس تم إبادتهم،
slowly and painfully.
ببطء وبكل ألم.
The international community responded with massive humanitarian relief,
كانت إستجابة المجتمع الدولي هي مساعدات إنسانية ضخمة،
and hundreds of thousands of more lives were saved.
وتم إنقاذ مئات الآلاف أكثر من الأرواح.
American troops were sent to protect the relief shipments,
تم إرسال جنود أمريكان لحماية شحنات الإغاثة،
but they were eventually drawn into the conflict,
لكنهم في نهاية المُطاف تم سحبهم إلى دائرة الصراع،
and after the tragic battle in Mogadishu, they were withdrawn.
وبعد المعركة المأساوية في مقديشو، انسحبوا منها.
In southern Sudan, another civil war saw similar use of starvation
في جنوب السودان، شهدت حرب أهلية أخرى مماثلة استخدام التجويع
as a means of genocide.
كوسيلة من وسائل الإبادة الجماعية.
Again, international NGOs, united under the umbrella of the U.N.,
مرة أخرى، منظمات الإغاثة الدولية، متحدة تحت غطاء الأمم المتحدة،
staged a massive relief operation and thousands of lives were saved.
قامت بعمليات إغاثة ضخمة وتم حفظ آلالاف الأرواح.
I'm a witness, and I want my testimony to be honest and uncensored.
أنا شاهد، وأريد أن تكون شهادتي صادقة وغير خاضعة للرقابة.
I also want it to be powerful and eloquent,
وأيضاً أريدها أن تكون قوية وبليغة،
and to do as much justice as possible
ولتخدم أقصى ما يمكن العدالة
to the experience of the people I'm photographing.
لتجربة الناس الذين أقوم بتصويرهم.
This man was in an NGO feeding center,
هذا الرجل كان في مركز تقديم الطعام لمنظمة طوعية،
being helped as much as he could be helped.
تم مساعدته بأقصى ما يستطيع تلقي المساعدة.
He literally had nothing. He was a virtual skeleton,
لقد كان حرفياً لا يملك شئ. لقد كان هيكلاً إفتراضياً،
yet he could still summon the courage and the will to move.
إلا أنه لا يزال يتمالك الشجاعة والإرادة للمضي.
He had not given up, and if he didn't give up,
لا يملك شيئاً ليتركه، وإذا لم يقم هو بالإستسلام،
how could anyone in the outside world ever dream of losing hope?
فكيف يمكن لأي شخص في العالم بأن يحلم بالتخلي عن الأمل؟
In 1994, after three months of covering the South African election,
عام 1994، بعد ثلاثة أشهر من تغطية إنتخابات جنوب أفريقيا،
I saw the inauguration of Nelson Mandela,
لقد شهدت حفل تنصيب نيلسون مانديلا،
and it was the most uplifting thing I've ever seen.
وقد كان أكثر شئ رفعةً رأيته على الإطلاق.
It exemplified the best that humanity has to offer.
لقد مثّل أفضل ما تستطيع الإنسانية تقديمه.
The next day I left for Rwanda,
في اليوم التالي غادرت إلى رواندا،
and it was like taking the express elevator to hell.
ولقد كانت مثل أخذ المصعد الفائف السرعة إلى جهنم.
This man had just been liberated from a Hutu death camp.
هذا الرجل تم تحريره للتو من معسكر الهوتو للموت.
He allowed me to photograph him for quite a long time,
لقد سمح لي بتصويره لوقت طويل نسبياً،
and he even turned his face toward the light,
وحتى أنه قام بتدوير رأسه تجاه الضوء،
as if he wanted me to see him better.
كما لو أنه أراد أن أراه بصورة أفضل.
I think he knew what the scars on his face would say to the rest of the world.
أعتقد أنه عرف ما ستقوله الندوب على وجهه لبقية العالم.
This time, maybe confused or discouraged
هذه المرة، ربما مرتبك أو غير متشجع
by the military disaster in Somalia,
بالكارثة العسكرية في الصومال،
the international community remained silent,
ظلّ المجتمع الدولي صامتاً،
and somewhere around 800,000 people were slaughtered
وفي مكان ما ذُبح حوالي 800،000 شخص
by their own countrymen -- sometimes their own neighbors --
من قبل مواطنيهم-- بعض الأحيان من قبل جيرانهم --
using farm implements as weapons.
باستخدام المحراث المستخدم كأسلحة.
Perhaps because a lesson had been learned
ربما لأن درساً قد تم تعلمه
by the weak response to the war in Bosnia
من الإستجابة الضعيفة للحرب في البوسنة
and the failure in Rwanda,
وفشل آخر في رواندا،
when Serbia attacked Kosovo,
عندما هاجمت صربيا كوسوفو
international action was taken much more decisively.
التحرك الدولي الحاسم تم بأسرع من ذلك بكثير.
NATO forces went in, and the Serbian army withdrew.
تدخلت قوات الناتو، وأنسحب الجيش الصربي.
Ethnic Albanians had been murdered,
وقد قُتل الألبانيين،
their farms destroyed and a huge number of people forcibly deported.
ودُمرت مزارعهم وأُجبرت أعداد ضخمة من الناس على الرحيل قسراً.
They were received in refugee camps
لقد تم إستقبالهم في معسكرات اللاجئين
set up by NGOs in Albania and Macedonia.
التي أقامتها المنظمات الطوعية في البانيا ومغدونيا.
The imprint of a man who had been burned inside his own home.
بصمة الرجل الذي تم إحراقه داخل منزله الخاص.
The image reminded me of a cave painting,
الصورة ذكرتني بالرسم على الكهوف،
and echoed how primitive we still are in so many ways.
ورددت صدى كم نحن ما نزال بدائيون في بالعديد من الطرق.
in Chechnya from inside Grozny.
في الشيشان من داخل غروزني.
This is a Chechen rebel on the front line against the Russian army.
هذا هو متمرد شيشاني على خط المواجهة مع الجيش الروسي.
The Russians bombarded Grozny constantly for weeks,
أمطر الروس غروزني بالقنابل لأسابيع باستمرار
killing mainly the civilians who were still trapped inside.
قاتلين معظم المدنيين الذين كانوا محاصرين بالداخل.
to a focus on critical social issues as well.
للتركيز على قضايا إجتماعية أيضاً.
and discovered a kind of gulag of children,
وأكتشفت نوعاً من معسكرات الأطفال،
where thousands of orphans were being kept in medieval conditions.
حيث مئات الإيتام تم الإبقاء عليهم في ظروف القرون الوسطى.
Ceausescu had imposed a quota
نظام تشاوشيسكو فرض نظام الحصص
on the number of children to be produced by each family,
على عدد من الأطفال الذين يجب أن تنجبهم كل أسرة،
thereby making women's bodies an instrument of state economic policy.
مما يجعل جسد المرأة أداة لسياسة الدولة الاقتصادية.
Children who couldn't be supported by their families
الأطفال الذين لا يتلقوا الدعم من أسرهم
were raised in government orphanages.
تم تربيتهم في دور الأيتام الحكومية.
Children with birth defects were labeled incurables,
والأطفال الذين يعانون من التشوهات الخلقية وُصفوا بالعضولون،
and confined for life to inhuman conditions.
وتقتصر حياتهم على ظروف لا إنسانية.
As reports began to surface, again international aid went in.
بينما بدأت التقارير الظهور على السطح، مجدداً تدفقت المساعدات الدولية.
Going deeper into the legacy of the Eastern European regimes,
بالذهاب أعمق إلى تركة دول أوروبا الشرقية،
I worked for several months on a story about the effects of industrial pollution,
لقد عملت عدة أشهر على قصة حول تأثير التلوث الصناعي،
where there had been no regard for the environment
حيث لم يكن هناك إهتمام بالبيئة
or the health of either workers or the general population.
أو بالصحة لكلٌ من العمال أو العامة.
An aluminum factory in Czechoslovakia
مصنع ألمونيوم في تشيكوسلوفاكيا
was filled with carcinogenic smoke and dust,
مغطى بالأدخنة والأبخرة المسببة للسرطان،
and four out of five workers came down with cancer.
واربعة من كل خمسة عمال أصيبوا بالسرطان.
I began to explore conditions of poverty
بدأت في إستكشاف أحوال الفقر
I spent a good deal of time with a man
لقد قضيت وقتاً طويلاً مع رجل
who lived with his family on a railway embankment
عاش مع أسرته على جسر السكك الحديدية
and had lost an arm and a leg in a train accident.
وقد فقد يده ورجله في حادث قطار.
When the story was published, unsolicited donations poured in.
عندما تم نشر القصة، تدفقت تبرعات بلا دعوة.
A trust fund was established,
تم تأسيس صندوق تأمين،
and the family now lives in a house in the countryside
وتعيش الأسرة الآن في منزل في الريف
and all their basic necessities are taken care of.
وتم العناية بكل إحتياجاتهم الضرورية.
It was a story that wasn't trying to sell anything.
لقد كانت قصة لا تحاول بيع أي شئ.
Journalism had provided a channel
وفّرت الصحافة القناة
for people's natural sense of generosity, and the readers responded.
لشعور الناس الطبيعي بالكرم، وقد أستجاب القُراء.
I met a band of homeless children who'd come to Jakarta from the countryside,
لقد إلتقيت بعصبة من الأطفال المشردين الذين جاءوا إلى جاكرتا من الريف،
and ended up living in a train station.
وأنتهى بهم الحال بالعيش في محطة القطار.
By the age of 12 or 14, they'd become beggars and drug addicts.
ببلوغهم سن 12 إلى 14، لقد اصبحوا شحاتين ومدمني مخدرات.
The rural poor had become the urban poor,
أصبح فقراء الريف هم فقراء المناطق الحضرية،
and in the process, they'd become invisible.
وبهذه العملية أصبحوا غير مرئيين.
These heroin addicts in detox in Pakistan
هؤلاء هم مدمني الهيروين في ديتوكس في باكستان
reminded me of figures in a play by Beckett:
ذكروني بالشخصيات في مسرحية بيكيت:
Agent Orange was a defoliant used during the Vietnam War
العامل البرتقالي كانت أوراق النباتات التي أستخدمت خلال حرب فيتنام
that was sprayed in vast quantities,
التي تم رشها بكميات ضخمة،
and whose effects passed through the genes to the next generation.
والتي يُورث تأثيرها عبر الجينات إلى الجيل التالي.
In 2000, I began documenting global health issues,
عام 2000، بدأت في توثيق قضايا الصحة العالمية،
concentrating first on AIDS in Africa.
بالتركيز أولاً على الإيدز في أفريقيا.
I tried to tell the story through the work of caregivers.
حاولت أن أسرد قصة عبر عمل مختصي الصحة.
I thought it was important to emphasize that people were being helped,
لقد فكرت بأنه من المهم التشديد على أن الناس تم مساعدتهم،
whether by international NGOs or by local grassroots organizations.
سواء من قبل المنظمات الدولية أو من قبل المنظمات الشعبية المحلية.
that grandmothers have taken the place of parents,
بحيث أخذت الجدات والأجداد مكان الآباء،
and a lot of children had been born with HIV.
ووُلد الكثير من الأطفال وهم مصابون بمرض نقص المناعة.
A hospital in Zambia.
مستشفى في زامبيا.
I began documenting the close connection
لقد بدأت بتوثيق الرابط الوثيق
between HIV/AIDS and tuberculosis.
ما بين نقص المناعة المكتسبة\الإيدز مع الُسل.
This is an MSF hospital in Cambodia.
هذه مستشفى أطباء بلا حدود في كمبوديا.
My pictures can play a supporting role to the work of NGOs
يمكن لصوري أن تلعب دوراً داعماً لعمل المنظمات الطوعية
I went to Congo with MSF,
لقد ذهبت إلى الكونغو مع أطباء بلا حدود،
and contributed to a book and an exhibition
وساهمت في كتاب ومعرض
that focused attention on a forgotten war
الذي ركّز الإنتباه على المنسيين من الحرب
in which millions of people have died,
التي مات فيها ملايين الناس،
and exposure to disease without treatment is used as a weapon.
ولأن يسخدم المرض بدون توفير العلاج، كسلاح.
A malnourished child being measured
طفل يعاني من سوء التغذية يجري قياسه
as part of the supplemental feeding program.
كجزء من برنامج التغذية التكميلية.
In the fall of 2004 I went to Darfur.
في خريف عام 2004 ذهبت إلى دارفور.
This time I was on assignment for a magazine,
هذه المرة كنت في مهمة من أجل مجلة،
but again worked closely with MSF.
لكن مرة أخرى عملت بتعاون وثيق مع أطباء بلا حدود.
The international community still hasn't found a way
لا يزال المجتمع الدولي لم يجد طريقاً
to create the pressure necessary to stop this genocide.
لعمل الضغط اللازم لإيقاف هذه الإبادة الجماعية.
A prisoner on a chain gang in Alabama
سجين مكبل بسلسلة في الباما
This experience raised a lot of questions,
أثارت هذه التجربة الكثير من الأسئلة،
among them questions about race and equality
بينها أسئلة حول العرق والمساواة
and for whom in our country opportunities and options are available.
ولمن في بلدنا تتاح الفرص والخيارات.
In the yard of a chain gang in Alabama.
في ساحة سلسلة العصابات في الباما.
and I thought it might have been an accident.
وقد فكرت بأنه ربما يكون حادثاً.
A few minutes later when I looked again
بعد دقائق قليلة لاحقاً عندما نظرت مجدداً
and saw the second tower burning, I knew we were at war.
ورأيت البرج الثاني يحترق، عرفت بأننا في حرب.
In the midst of the wreckage at Ground Zero, I had a realization.
في وسط الحطام في غراوند زيرو، كان لدي إعتقاد.
not only in the Middle East, but also in Africa, Asia and Europe.
ليس فقط في الشرق الأوسط، لكن أيضاً في أفريقيا، آسيا وأوروبا.
At the time I was photographing in these different places,
في الوقت الذي كنت أقوم بتصوير هذه المناطق المختلفة،
I thought I was covering separate stories,
فكرت بأنني أغطي قصص منفصلة.
but on 9/11 history crystallized, and I understood
لكن في تاريخ 9/11 تبلورت، وقد فهمت
I'd actually been covering a single story for more than 20 years,
لقد كنت في الواقع أغطي قصة واحدة لأكثر من 20 عاماً،
The central commercial district of Kabul, Afghanistan
المنطقة المركزية التجارية في كابول، أفغانستان
at the end of the civil war,
عند نهاية الحرب الأهلية،
shortly before the city fell to the Taliban.
قبل فترة وجيزة من سقوط المدينة على يد طالبان.
at the Red Cross rehab center being run by Alberto Cairo.
في رحاب الصليب الأحمر الذي يديره ألبرتو كايرو.
A boy who lost a leg to a leftover mine.
الطفل الذي فقد ساقه في إنفجار بقايا لغم.
I'd witnessed immense suffering in the Islamic world
لقد كنت شاهداً على المعاناة الرهيبة في العالم الإسلامي
from political oppression, civil war, foreign invasions, poverty, famine.
من القمع السياسي، الحرب الأهلية، الغزو الأجنبي، الفقر، المجاعة.
I understood that in its suffering,
لقد فهمت بأنه خلال معانتهم،
the Islamic world had been crying out. Why weren't we listening?
كانت العالم الإسلامي يصرخ. لماذا لم نكن نستمع؟
A Taliban fighter shot during a battle
مقاتل طالباني تم قتله خلال معركة
as the Northern Alliance entered the city of Kunduz.
حيث دخل التحالف الشمالي لمدينة كوندوز.
When war with Iraq was imminent,
عندما باتت حرب العراق وشيكة،
I realized the American troops would be very well covered,
أدركت بأن القوات الأمريكية ستكون مغطاة بشكل جيد،
so I decided to cover the invasion from inside Baghdad.
لذا فقد قررت تغطية الغزو من داخل بغداد.
A marketplace was hit by a mortar shell
سوق تم قصفه بقذيفة هاون
that killed several members of a single family.
قتلت عدة أفراد من أسرة واحدة.
A day after American forces entered Baghdad,
بعد يوم من دخول القوات الأمريكية إلى بغداد،
a company of Marines began rounding up bank robbers
مجموعة من مشاة البحرية يعتلقون لصوص بنك
and were cheered on by the crowds --
وقد تمت تحيتهم من قبل الجموع --
a hopeful moment that was short lived.
لحظة أمل عاشت للحظات قصيرة.
to Karbala to observe Ashura,
إلى كربلاء للإحتفال بذكرى عاشوراء،
and I was amazed by the sheer number of people
وقد كنت مذهولاً بالعدد الماهول من الناس
and how fervently they practiced their religion.
وكيف كانوا يؤدون شعائر دينهم.
A group of men march through the streets cutting themselves with knives.
مجموعة من الرجال يسيرون عبر الطرق يطعنون أنفسهم بالسكاكين.
It was obvious that the Shi'ites were a force to be reckoned with,
وكان واضحا أن الشيعة يمثلون قوة لا يستهان بها،
and we would do well to understand them and learn how to deal with them.
وسنفعل حسناً إن أستطعنا فهمهم وتعلّم كيفية التعامل معهم.
Last year I spent several months documenting our wounded troops,
العام الماضي قضيت عدة أشهر في توثيق جنودنا الجرحى،
from the battlefield in Iraq all the way home.
من ساحة المعركة في العراق طوال طريقهم إلى الوطن.
to a soldier who had been shot in the head.
للجندي الذي تم إصابته في الرأس.
that the percentage of troops who survive after being wounded
بحيث أن نسبة القوات التي تنجو بعد إصابتهم
The signature weapon of the war is the IED,
السلاح الأبرز للحرب هو العبوات الناسفة،
and the signature wound is severe leg damage.
و الإصابة الأبرز هي ضرر بالغ في الساق.
the wounded face a grueling physical
الوجه المصاب للقسوة البدنية
and psychological struggle in rehab.
والمعاناة النفسية في المصحة.
I tried to imagine myself in their place,
لقد حاولت تخيل نفسي في أوضاعهم،
and I was totally humbled by their courage and determination
وكنت أتواضع تماماً من شجاعتهم وتصميمهم
in the face of such catastrophic loss.
في مواجهة مثل هذه الخسائر الفادحة.
and all these guys who'd never surfed before said, "Hey, let's go."
وكل أؤلئك الناس الذين لم يتزلجوا مطلقاً بالقول، " هيا، لنذهب."
And they went surfing.
وقد ذهبوا للتزلج.
Photographers go to the extreme edges of human experience
يمضي المصورون إلى أقصى حدود التجربة الإنسانية
to show people what's going on.
ليعرضوا للناس ما يجري.
Sometimes they put their lives on the line,
بعض الأحيان يضعون حياتهم على المحك،
because they believe your opinions and your influence matter.
لأنهم يؤمنون بأن آرائك وتأثيرك مهم.
They aim their pictures at your best instincts,
إنهم يستهدفون بصورهم لأفضل مافي غرائزكم،
generosity, a sense of right and wrong,
بكل كرم، بشعور الصواب والخطأ،
the ability and the willingness to identify with others,
والقدرة والرغبة بالكشف مع آخرين،
the refusal to accept the unacceptable.
لرفض قبول ما لا يمكن قبوله.
My TED wish:
أمنيتي لجائزة تيد:
there's a vital story that needs to be told,
هناك قصص حيوية ينبغي أن تُحكى،
and I wish for TED to help me gain access to it
وأتمنى أن يساعدني تيد للحصول على إمكانية الوصول لها
and then to help me come up with innovative and exciting ways
ثم ليساعدني للوصول إلى طرق مبتكرة ومثيرة
to use news photography in the digital era.
لإستخدام تصوير الاخبار في العصر الرقمي.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)